"Previously on The Mentalist..."
"I can't do this anymore."
"I can't watch you
do this work. I mean..."
It coulda been you
in that coffin.
You can't keep pulling me from
the path of oncoming trains.
I'm leaving.
I have to go.
- But why Greece?
- It's the cradle of civilization.
Well, yeah, like
3 thousand years ago.
Uh, what have they done
for us lately?
Okay, so, where should I go?
You...
You should stay.
Study abroad is overrated.
What?
- Is somebody out there?
- Don't even joke about that.
Donnie, go!
Please... Don't, please.
- Morning, Lisbon.
- Cho...
Uh, this is Park Ranger
Jill Ayres.
Uh, she was the first person
on the crime scene.
- Glad to have the FBI's help.
- Happy to be here.
- Who found 'em?
- I did.
I was doing
my morning rounds.
I saw the tire tracks
going off the side.
Any idea what they were doin'
out here?
Well, it's a nice view,
from the top of the hill.
Kids come out here to park.
Techs found nine millimeter casings
at the top of the hill
next to the tire tracks.
So, the shooting took place
up there.
They go the wrong way
and end up down here.
She try to make
a run for it?
Uh, there are drag marks
from the car to the body
so, the killer must have
moved her.
Maybe he was searching
for something.
Maybe the killer tried to take
the body up the hill
and got to that steep part...
Realized it wasn't gonna happen.
- But why move her at all?
- That's a good question.
Thank you, Ranger.
We'll be in touch.
You bet.
The vultures are here.
Great.
We could use
Jane's read on this.
It's been a week.
You haven't heard from him?
No. No, not since the funeral.
All right, well, Abbott's starting
to prep his move to DC.
We're shorthanded.
We need to close this
before it gets out of hand.
Now's not the time for one
of his disappearing acts.
You want me to call him?
- No. Nah, I'll call him.
- Okay.
Wylie's doing background checks
on Donnie and Megan.
We can't seem to find any reason
somebody would want them dead.
They seem like a couple
of nice college kids.
Sometimes, national parks
are used by drug cultivators.
Now, maybe these kids were at
the wrong place, at the wrong time.
We've got a contact in the park rangers.
I can ask her to come in.
Anything come back
from forensics?
Uh, they were both killed
with the same gun: 9mm.
- Hm.
- No hits from ballistics.
- Autopsy turned up somethin'.
- What?
Both Donnie and Megan
were missing a fingernail.
They didn't lose it
in the crash?
The ME thinks
they were pulled out.
Huh, Add that to Megan's body
being moved
and this case is startin'
to feel pretty strange.
Good work.
So, no word from Jane, huh?
Uh, he's not returning my calls.
I know you two are working
something out...
but these murders are starting
to get headline news.
- We need Jane.
- I'm handling it.
Okay.
Afternoon, Officer.
Sir, are you the registered
owner of this vehicle?
- I am.
- May I see your license, please?
Sure.
So, you are Patrick Jane.
All day, every day... Unfortunately.
- Step out of the vehicle.
- Okay.
- Hands up.
- All right.
Okay.
Thorough.
Sir, you have a warrant out
for your arrest in Austin, Texas.
- What's the charge?
- Failure to appear.
Oh, yeah, that's funny.
- Thanks for coming in.
- Glad to.
Have a seat.
Nice office.
I don't get a lot
of air conditioning in my life.
Anything going down in the park
that we should know about?
Like what?
Something Donnie and Megan
may have seen
that somebody didn't want
them to see?
Maybe a drug operation?
Uh, we did a major sweep
of the park a few months ago
cleaned it out.
Poachers.
We've been finding deer
in the forest
just the backstrap cut out.
Any idea who's behind it?
The best bet's a couple of fellows
with a shack
just outside the park.
The Whitmer brothers.
Marcus Whitmer's on probation
for aggravated assault.
Hey.
Yeah, looks fresh.
- The hell is this?
- FBI. Put the knife down, sir.
Put the gun on the ground.
Do it now.
It's all right.
Do what he says, Marcus.
Do it now!
Hey!
Turn over!
- Come on!
- Agent Cho!
Cuff him!
I didn't know you were law.
I wasn't gonna shoot you.
Damn near busted my ribs.
Get up.
You know if Donnie and Megan
were planning to meet
with anyone
when they left the dorm?
Of course... Just something
we have to ask.
Uh, well, if you think of anything
or hear anything
please, give us a call.
Thank you.
Excuse me... Hi.
- Can I help you?
- My name's Ree Osbourne.
I'm here about the two
that were shot last night
The two in the forest.
Do you have information
about the case?
No, I don't.
My brother does.
- That's your brother?
- Yeah. Gabriel.
I'm Agent Wylie.
What do you know
about the murders?
He's shy.
I had to drag him over here.
He doesn't like talking
but I told him he had to say
what he saw.
He witnessed the crime?
No, he didn't witness it.
He saw it.
In his head?
- You mean, he's a psychic?
- Yeah... Psychic.
Gabriel.
Come over here.
Tell this man what you have to say.
He's loud.
I'm loud?
The crying is loud.
I hear you crying, inside.
- What are you talking about?
- I'm so sorry.
See, I don't think
my brother's a psychic.
I know he's a psychic.
Can you please
come with me?
The poachers were out
hunting wild boar
12 hours away, last night.
There's a liquor store clerk
three counties over
that confirms their story.
They got back
just before Cho arrived.
Hm. Well, we're not gettin' anything
from friends or family either.
They sound like
regular college kids.
We've got the UT campus covered.
We talked to friends,
classmates, professors.
Come in.
You got somethin'?
I have a guy who's saying
things about the murders.
Well, what is he saying, Wylie?
- He's a psychic.
- Ah, come on.
I, I don't know how to explain it...
You need to talk to him.
- You're leaving.
- Excuse me?
You're moving on.
You're going to a new place.
- Yeah.
- Eager to go.
You have doubts inside
you haven't told anybody.
Everybody has doubt
when they're going through
a change in their life.
Tell us what you know
about the murders of
Donald Putnam
and Megan Brooks.
The killer, he wanted
to take them with him.
He wanted them.
But he couldn't.
Took a piece of them, instead.
Fingertips.
So... I didn't say
that would be helpful.
I only said it would be true.
How do you know
about this?
Six months ago,
I spoke to a man.
He had so much wrongness in him,
I could hardly look at him.
It was like starin' at the sun.
I been waiting ever since
for somethin' like this
- to happen.
- Who was he?
I don't know.
Okay. What did he look like?
He was a man.
He was white.
Sorry, I'm not good with faces.
I only see what's inside.
So, he met the killer
but he can't remember
a single detail about him.
I agree.
That's suspicious.
But he knew about the bodies
being moved
and he knew
about the fingernails.
Which we already knew.
But none of those details
have been made public.
Oh, maybe he's friends
with the crime tech...
Or maybe he's the killer.
And he just marched in here
and dangled himself
right in front of us?
It's more likely than him being
an actual honest-to-god psychic.
What makes you so sure?
Years of experience.
What were you doin'
in Arizona?
- I went to the Grand Canyon.
- The Grand Canyon.
Mm.
- Have you been?
- No. Nah, I hear it's big.
Huge, yeah.
How's the tea?
Hot. Good. Thank you.
I woulda mailed you your cup
but I didn't know where you were.
Well, you knew I'd be back.
No, I didn't.
I can't read minds.
The first time I called you,
I thought, "he missed my call".
Second time, I thought,
"He's busy."
"Okay, he'll call me back"
The third time,
I thought, "He's dead."
"He is dead in a ditch,
on the side of the road"
I didn't mean to scare you.
- Well, you did scare me.
- I'm sorry.
Okay.
I'm working through something
and I just need space to think.
I can't soldier on,
like you, Lisbon.
We're all upset.
I can't just run away
from my work here.
This job is too important to me.
Yeah, I understand.
What can I do for you to help you
figure things out?
- Just tell me.
- Time. I just need some time.
Okay.
Time's good.
I can give you time.
- I just need one thing from you.
- What's that?
- Don't ignore my phone calls.
- Okay. Well, that's. That's fair.
All right.
Ah, Jane, welcome back.
Not back, just stopping by.
Oh, yeah, I figured.
Hey, do you have a minute?
I was wondering if you would take
a look at someone that just left.
Abbott, I'm, I'm...
Jane, you would find him
very interesting.
Gabriel, could I have a moment
of your time?
Patrick Jane.
I'm with the FBI.
I just want to ask you
a few questions.
You're an FBI agent?
- He is not.
- He's right.
You, you knew that
because you're a psychic?
I knew that
because I'm not stupid.
You knew that because of the way
I dress, my posture
the way I cut my hair...
Any number of things.
What do you want from me?
Well, I'm a student of the form.
Just wanted
to shake your hand.
Think I'm a fraud?
I don't think you're a fraud.
You are a fraud.
Might just be looking at
your reflection in a mirror.
Then make a prediction for me.
- So you can mock it?
- Maybe.
There's a thing inside you.
It's eating you.
A thing that's lingered
in your mind for many years.
That's called
the human condition.
- You'll be cured.
- Wonderful.
Cure will come
with the number three.
"The number three"...
Huh. That's it?
I could embellish it.
That'd be a lie.
Number three.
You'll know it when you see it.
Thanks for your time.
So, what do you think?
Well, he's obviously not
a real psychic
but he knows what he's doing.
He's very smart, very controlled.
Either that,
or he's an insane killer.
I'd keep an eye on him.
Will do.
Did you find anything
in his background?
Clean criminal record.
He's Austin-born and raised
former used-bookstore clerk.
Currently unemployed.
Does he have an alibi
for the night of the murders?
Wylie checked. No alibi.
Well... if he isn't our killer
maybe he's plugged
into the murders
in a way
we don't understand yet.
- We should put a tail on him.
- Yeah, you do that.
Uh, one more thing.
Ranger Ayres told me about your
encounter with the poachers.
- Okay.
- Well, she said that
you came on a little strong
with one of 'em.
- Is that what happened?
- He caught me by surprise.
I was a little aggressive
in the moment.
It won't happen again.
- Is there anything else goin' on?
- Like what?
Well...
We're all still feeling
Vega's death.
I know I am.
Did the Army assign you
a counselor
- when you left Special Forces?
- They did.
Might be time to get in touch
with him again.
It's good to talk to someone.
It's helping me.
I'll think about it.
Anything else?
Nope, that's it.
Hey.
Thanks.
No problem.
Cho?
- Cho?
- Yeah?
Can I come with you?
It's just that I, I know
you're shorthanded
and I thought
maybe I could be useful.
When was the last time
you shot your weapon?
Couple days ago.
I stay current.
All right.
Get some dinner.
Be ready in an hour.
Okay.
Closing time.
I'm kicking you out.
Oh, come on,
I have a free game here.
Okay, tell you what.
You bring me that case of beer
and put it over there
and I'll let you play
your free game.
You got it.
My pleasure, Angela?
Amy?
Arlene?
How do you know my name
starts with an "A"?
'Cause a person
with the initials APJ
has all the high scores
on that machine over there
Somethin' to pass the time
on those quiet nights.
Yep.
APJ likes to play pinball
instead of wiping down
the beer cooler.
That's a very clever trick.
Well, it's not rocket surgery.
Looks like you have
three free games.
Three, that's what I'm talkin' about.
He thinks he's gonna impress me
with "three."
How's that, now?
Well, three's meaningful to you.
Yeah. It is.
How'd you know?
Mm, well, because three
is meaningful to everyone.
I say three and you're impressed
because you have three kids.
Wait, now. How do you know
I have three kids?
I don't.
I, I was just guessing.
That's what I mean. I...
I'm gonna...
Don't worry 'bout that.
I'm gonna settle up my account.
- How much do I owe you?
- You paid already.
- Did I leave you a tip?
- Yep.
- Was it a good tip?
- Yeah.
- Well, that's nice.
- Mm-hm.
Mm, hey, whoa. Okay.
Just sleep it off on the couch
in the back.
Keys'll be there in the morning.
Coffee and aspirin, too.
Well, that's a very generous
offer, Adriana, thank you.
- Mm-mm.
- Nope, okay.
But I think
I'm gonna walk it off.
- I need to clear my head.
- Suit yourself.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Amber!
Are you sure
you're not psychic?
That is the one thing
I am very sure I am not.
- Hm.
- 'Night!
Good night.
I feel like this is a job
that'll be replaced
by robots someday.
Someday soon.
This is being in the field.
It's not all action.
Right.
Is this any good?
It's Dostoevsky.
Is that good or bad?
Okay.
Morning.
Oh, come on.
Who's that?
Neighbor. Five doors down.
- What are they doing?
- Talking.
- Should we write that down?
- No.
So, I bet Vega was pretty good
at all this stuff, right?
- Yeah, she was.
- Thought so.
Hey.
If you wanna be out here,
I can show you the ropes.
But do it because you want to,
not because you miss her, okay?
I'm just tired
of being back in the office
when you could use me
out here.
- I'm ready.
- Okay.
Stay here,
watch the house.
Excuse me, ma'am?
I'm Agent Cho, FBI.
Whoa, okay,
what's going on?
I have a few questions about
your neighbor, Gabriel Osbourne?
Oh.
What were you talking about?
- Nothing.
- You sat there for three minutes
talking about nothing?
I asked him
if I was gonna find love.
- I have a date tonight.
- You go to Gabriel often?
I know how it sounds.
It's crazy, I know.
But I used to date this guy
and Gabriel told me
he was married
and he had never met him,
he just knew.
I don't believe in psychics.
But I believe in Gabriel.
Cho!
Gabriel!
Gabriel, hang tight.
It's gonna be okay.
- What happened?
- I don't... I don't know.
- He just collapsed.
- I'll call an ambulance.
Gabriel... Gabriel!
- You.
- Yeah?
She says she's okay.
She says...
Who are you talking about?
The pain is all gone, okay?
She says she's okay.
You don't gotta be sad anymore.
Are you talking about Michelle?
- What's going on?
- What?
It's red clay.
It's white bones,
and they're wrapped in red clay.
Did you get an update
from the hospital
on Gabriel's condition?
He refused to go to the hospital.
He doesn't trust doctors.
- He needs to see a doctor.
- Yeah. We tried.
You workin' on a new lead?
This is where Donnie Putnam
and Megan Brooks were killed.
But this area is interesting.
What about it?
This area here is known
for its red clay deposits.
It's less than a mile
from the murder scene.
- Okay.
- Gabriel said something.
He had a, a, a vision
after his seizure.
He said something
about white bones in red Clay.
Wylie... You know Gabriel's
not a real psychic.
I think we should look
into this area.
We can't go
on a wild-goose chase
because of something
Gabriel said.
- You okay?
- Yeah.
- You sure?
- Yeah. Yeah, I'm fine.
This isn't about Vega, okay?
This is about a real lead.
It wouldn't hurt to look,
would it?
All right.
We'll look into it.
- So, what do you think?
- Eh, ground's tough.
Don't know what you expect
to find here.
It's a shot in the dark
but can't hurt to take a look.
We'll go up and back,
up and back
'til we cover the area.
If Nicky smells something
worth checking out
he'll bark twice like this.
Okay, thanks.
What did Gabriel say to you?
He said, "white bones
wrapped in red clay."
I know that. What else?
And what did he say
to make you believe in him?
- He said she's okay.
- Who?
Michelle. She's okay.
Wherever she is
she's okay.
And he knew
where she was shot.
Vega's death was on the news.
It's no secret.
It didn't feel like that.
- He's not a real psychic, Wylie.
- You can't know that.
You can't know that for sure.
Jane, I'm glad
I could find you.
Well, I'm trying to be
more findable these days.
"You know. Look, we're running
a ghost ship right now."
We need you.
Are you ready to come in?
Uh, yeah,
I think I can do that.
Are you nearby?
Well, to be honest,
I have no idea where I am.
I know I missed your call
last night.
I, I, I didn't...
I didn't mean to.
I'm sorry.
- What are you doin' here?
- I'm back.
What does that mean exactly:
"You're back"?
Well, it means
I'm figuring stuff out.
I'm, I'm figuring it out.
It's good to you see you.
It's good to see you, too.
So, what's goin' on here?
You came just in time.
Come on.
So I see.
We're lookin'
for a serial killer.
Five victims, all killed
using the same gun
that killed Donnie Putnam
and Megan Brooks.
They were all killed
in the past year.
They all had
their fingernails removed.
So we're looking
for a serial killer.
The first three victims
had no IDs on them.
That and the way they were
dressed leads me to believe
that they were either homeless
or drifters.
Victims four and five
were foreign-exchange students
that were reported missing
two months ago.
Add Megan and Donnie it brings the total
number of victims to seven.
We'll consult with
the profilers at Quantico.
Help expand the search
and see if there's any other
consistent patterns
with the other victims.
- What about the media?
- Eh, we'll sit on it.
Gabriel Osbourne took us
to a field
that had five bodies
buried in it.
If he didn't do it,
he knows who did.
All right, I'll bring him in.
Now, he won't ever admit it,
but he's in pain.
It's like you met him.
Not here just to talk.
- I'm gonna go with you?
- That's right.
- Are you arresting me?
- If that's how you want it.
Gabriel, is everything all right?
Call my sister.
Hey. Heard you had a spell.
How are you feeling now?
Fine.
Get tired but I'm okay.
Something different about you
from the last time we talked.
You look lighter.
Less conflicted.
Number three, you saw it
and found an answer, huh?
The number three is incredibly
common, Gabriel.
We see it everywhere.
Red clay, little rarer.
But, uh, not much.
- I didn't wanna be right.
- Of course you did.
I don't wanna see
these things.
Okay, I don't ask
for these visions.
Yeah, visions are a real drag.
I know how you feel.
You can't know how I feel.
Yeah, I used to be you, Gabriel.
What is that supposed to mean?
You spent a year of your childhood
struggling with an illness.
That's when you learned
to love to read.
You used to play piano
but you didn't like it,
so you quit.
You're not half as unsure
of yourself as you pretend to be.
Who told you all that?
- My sister?
- Nobody. No one.
You're lying.
And you don't have visions.
No, I don't have visions,
and neither do you, Gabriel.
Why are you playing games
with me?
I need you to know that
I understand your little tricks.
I don't play tricks.
You're the one who's playing
tricks with me right now.
- I only wanna help.
- If you wanna help
you can start by telling me
how you know what you know.
I had another vision
you should know about.
I saw that the killer
is going to kill again.
Tonight.
And if you won't listen to me,
I'll tell everyone.
- Okay, I have to warn people.
- You can't leave.
- Why not?
- Because I came in here
to figure out
if you are just a fraud
or if you are a monster.
What did you decide?
You have to stay here, Gabriel.
We didn't find anything
at Gabriel's house.
Well, he's not breaking.
- He won't admit he's a fraud?
- Well, he's not a fraud.
Are you saying
he's really psychic?
- No.
- Then what is he?
I don't know. I don't...
We have to keep him here.
All right.
Excuse me, can I help you?
Where's my brother?
Do you have my brother?
I am Gabriel Osbourne's attorney.
I've come to secure his release
from the illegal arrest
you've placed him under.
Well, we only brought him in
for questioning.
I have a writ of habeas corpus
being couriered to Judge Decker.
Do I need to get him out of bed or are you
prepared to release Gabriel immediately?
Mr. Osbourne!
Give us a shot.
- Mr. Osbourne.
- Mr. Osbourne!
Mr. Osbourne,
I just have a few questions.
- Mr. Osbourne!
- Gabriel!
Ladies and gentlemen....
Ladies and gentlemen,
thank you for coming.
My client, Gabriel Osbourne has been
illegally detained by the FBI
for attempting to help them
capture a serial killer
A serial killer that is currently
on the loose in Austin.
Mr. Osbourne, we just need
to know a few things.
- Do you know any...
- Let's have Gabriel tell the story
in his own words.
I had a vision that helped them
find five bodies today.
They don't have
any suspects.
FBI thinks it was me.
They wanna frame me.
They wanna hide the truth.
There's a serial killer out there.
He is a man with an evil heart
and an appetite to kill.
He's not done killing.
He won't stop,
and he, he can't stop.
He's... He's gonna kill again.
That's all for now.
Thank you.
Stewart, Stewart, if we...
We just have a few more questions.
- "We wanna know more."
- This is going badly.
- Mr. Osbourne!
- Yes, it is.
But we're gonna stay focused
on finding the killer.
I'll stay on Gabriel.
You do that.
I'm gonna feed myself
to the sharks.
Great. Thanks for the update.
What's the word from the office?
Police lines are flooded.
People are seeing
serial killers everywhere.
And not a peep from these two.
Who's that?
What should we do?
You stay put.
I'll call you if I need you.
Stop, FBI!
C'mon out.
- You're the neighbor, right?
- Mm-hm.
- Why'd you run?
- I was scared.
Gabriel was on the news and said
there was a killer on the loose
and then I saw you lurking.
Okay, go on home.
Wylie, hey.
- What happened?
- I don't know. Somebody hit me.
- You all right?
- Yeah.
Come on, get up.
- Going in, okay? All right.
- Okay.
- Can I get a second?
- Yeah.
How you holdin' up?
I don't know.
I don't think I'm cut out
for the field.
This is rough work.
You're gonna get banged up
every once in a while.
I don't think I can do this.
You wanna go back to the office
and answer phones?
"Okay these guys..."
"That's correct."
No.
I wanna stay.
What can I do, here?
We need to put together
a description of your attacker.
I don't know if it was Gabriel
or someone else who attacked me
and now Gabriel's gone.
And Jane's inside.
Go see him.
- Why?
- Just go.
Hey. How you feelin'?
They wanna check me out
at the hospital
but Cho said
to see you first.
Hm. Yeah, what do you remember
about the person who attacked you?
Nothing. I didn't see the guy.
Oh, you know more
than you think you do.
I just want you
to close your eyes.
Okay, big breath in.
And out.
Good. One more...Breath.
Now, I want you to listen
very carefully to my voice.
You hear no other sound
other than my voice.
There's someone behind you.
You don't know who it is.
But you see something out
of the corner of your eye.
No. No, I don't see anything.
That's okay.
You're doing fine.
Right before you were hit
there was a scent in the air
A faint scent.
Mm. Yeah.
What was it?
I don't know.
Does it remind you of anything?
My Uncle's fishing shed.
Ah. Was it fish?
No. He doesn't actually fish there.
He just went there
to drink.
- What did he drink?
- Beer.
It smells like old, spilled beer.
- You did very well.
- Thanks.
Okay, I got it. Thanks.
Mustang Creek Brewery.
It shut down around a year ago.
It's only a mile from where
the bodies were found.
Let's go.
Get a perimeter set up,
three-block radius.
I got the front.